Well, you, you... Sorry, go ahead. [chuckles] That's never happened before. In
100 episodes, I don't think we've ever done what we just did.
What? Both tried to yield?
Well, yeah.
They don't know what I know. They don't know- Hey, it's Engineering Podcast. I'm
Adam
I'm Brian.
Welcome back for another hang in the laboratory. It's, uh, just the two of us
this week, and we don't need light, we don't need help keeping the lights on.
So, uh, let's do it. [laughs] How you doing, man?
Get out of here. We don't need your help. Uh, I am, uh-
This is episode 98
I'm doing pretty good
... and we don't, we don't know for sure what this project becomes at episode
100, so we're just kinda ticking them off when we have time.
Yeah. We're, we're, uh, [clears throat] we're just, uh, we're evolving. We're
changing. Things are happening. [laughs]
What, uh-
You're, uh, you're about to have a kid.
You're about to have a kid.
N- so not as soon as you.
Not as soon as me. Yeah.
[laughs]
It's funny to have a... We, we, because of medical circumstances, we have an
induction scheduled, so, like, that's weird. I got a hard out [laughs] on this
pregnancy.
I think that's smart. I know some people who have suggested that we do that
because then you're just scheduling things, but they won't let us do that at our
hospital.
Yeah, that's fair. Uh, but we're not here to talk about that.
No.
Partially, I think because we're both going through that, we'd rather talk about
an engineering topic, in a sense. It's sort of engineering. It's like
engineering cultural topic.
I'd rather nerd rage with you.
Nerd rage. What, uh... Yeah, so what, what's the, what's the topic? Give us our
intro, sir.
Yeah, I mean, you came all fired up to, uh, to discuss the concepts of open
source or open collaboration maybe it'll expand out to, but-
Yeah, I think-
... open source software more specifically
... uh, I, I am-- Juris is increasingly, and I am increasingly involved in other
projects that are ultimately built on top of open source software. Um, and so,
you know, that causes this engineering part of my brain to dig deeper and deeper
into the notions of, you know, both technologically what gets us to where we are
and how's that novel, and then, uh, culturally-
Mm-hmm
... like how does that get us to where we are, right? So, and the realization I
have as I cross the sort of... As I try to bridge rivers, I suppose. Um, you
know, I talk to a whole bunch of lawyers all the time, and I try to explain to
them the way that programmers think about the world in the modern world, and I
talk about things like version control, I talk about things like open source
software, and they just have no idea what I'm talking about. And then some
subset don't even believe that it's possible, even though we have everything in
front of us working. And I go, "Yeah, but this is working." And they go, "Mm, I
still don't buy it."
It's pretty crazy when the legal system is built on open source, right? Open
source-
Methodology. Yeah
... opinions, open source decisions, open sourced rules and documents, all
those, all those funny looking books that are just the same in the background of
every legal picture.
Right.
That's just open source legal stuff.
So-
I guess maybe you pay for them, so the open part's not... But it's kind of open
source, right?
Yeah, but it's not supposed to be paid for, and every time somebody challenges
that, the Supreme Court goes, "Yeah, you can't, you can't charge for that. It's
public." [laughs] Uh, yeah. So let's, so, so, so in this case, when you talk
about the laws, like it's easy to, it's easy to see that the laws are meant to
be public, right? Um, in this case, maybe the place to start is defining source,
'cause open's easy. We can, we can dig into open and what it means-
Is it?
... from a cultural standpoint.
Yeah.
But like the first thing that makes the movement that we, that you and I would
call open source work is the source code ultimately, right?
Yeah.
Source, open source sort of in, at least in the context you and I are talking
about, I think, 'cause like obviously source is a broad word. But like from
your, from your engineering perspective.
Yeah. It's an interesting question 'cause I always, with software I, I... It's
easy to kind of spiral down its, into its own little rabbit hole 'cause there's
something weird and unique about software and, and that feeling has faded a
little bit as I've, as I've progressed in that world in my life, but I'll never
forget when I first started really learning to program how strangely unique the
whole ecosystem is. Um, but [clears throat] yeah, the source code is, is the
program. It's the thing, it-- When you install an app on your, on your, uh,
phone, like you're downloading code kind of. I mean, there's a lot of other
stuff going on, but, uh, in theory, right? Back in the day when you used to like
get a floppy disk, uh, when I was a kid, and people would be like, "Hey, here's
a, here's a game," or, "Here's a whatever," uh, you're, you're just getting,
you're getting software, and then you, you bring it home and you put it on your
computer or you, or you download it into your phone. And then when you like tap
it or touch it or I don't even know if people use the word open [chuckles]
anymore. Do kids say, "I opened an app"?
When they load it. [laughs]
Right when they touch it. Uh, it, the computer runs the code. Like it's, it's
just... I mean, it's like a, it's kind of like-
Yeah. So-
... a Rube Goldberg machine behind the scenes. The computer's just making the
Rube Goldberg machine run.
Yeah. And like I think we got episodes on episodes about this stuff, if we wanna
chase it, if you wanna chase through our feed. But like, you know, ultimately a
computer is this processing mechanism, and it runs through a string of digits
written out that provide it with everything it needs to do all the sort of
conditional things that are run in an app, right? But underneath that is just a
bunch of code. Like it's a bunch of text. Like you could print out-Like macOS.
It would be reams and reams of paper, but you could print it out and go, "Yo,
here it is."
Yep.
Enter it back in and it'll run. [chuckles] And that's how they used to do
programming, on like pieces of paper, right? Uh, a- and-
Yeah
... but ultimately, like it, it gets weird because it's just text. And so even
from a legal standpoint, like immediately we're getting to the, the legal side,
the only way you can protect that is kind of the same ways you protect books and
things like that, right? Like you can copyright license your code, and so then
people have to pay you to use it. Uh, that's kinda it.
Well, it's interesting. Software is interesting technologically too because, uh,
it's different, it's different as an entity than like a car, for instance,
right? I, and I choose cars 'cause that's maybe one of the more complex things
that everybody owns and like deals with on a day-to-day basis. Like if you go
under the hood of your car, there's all kinds of stuff going on in there. Seems
like a mess, super complicated, and ignore the fact that there are tons of
computers and software in cars these days too. Let's just pretend it's all the
like moving parts. You got your motors and your pistons and your catalytic
converters and stuff. It's pretty complicated in there, but actually if you pull
everything out, it's like a known number of parts. You can even pull into those
and pull everything out, and you're talking like probably hundreds of thousands
of parts, like physical components, and those break down, ultimately down to
like a physical thing, like here's a bolt. Software is kind of, it's like
infinitely complex, right? Every line of code does something, and each line of
code could do that thing like an infinite number of ways. And so when you're
dealing with software as a, as like a technological entity, it-- there's,
there's this weird thing about it that just makes it like infinitely un- unique,
um, and infinitely customizable, and that kind of feeds into, I think, what
drives, uh, open source software and why it kind of emerges there. Um, [sighs]
do you get what I'm saying?
But it's not-
[laughs]
Yeah. I mean, and so this is the thing about having to cover the source piece,
'cause like it's not a new thing to say, "I'm not gonna try to protect." Like
this is why I get to the licensing part, right? Like if you invent a car, we
live in a governmental system where you get to go, "Okay, I can patent this
version of how to put these pieces together," which like nobody's gonna try to
do anyway 'cause it has to be done at great cost. But if they wanted to, they're
not even allowed to because I have the right to be the only one that does this
for a certain amount of time, and has to do with the laws that we've put in
place around market economics, et cetera, right? Like, but I think the key part
of that is, is, you know, um, [coughs] that I couldn't build a car if I wanted
to, right? It doesn't matter if I could get all of Honda's plans-
[chuckles]
... for like, you know, a Civic. I can't build a Civic. And so that market is
what it is, right?
Certainly not easily.
Like Tesla has open sourced all of their patents. It's no help to me unless I'm
gonna go start a competing car company, right? So like it's funny that they hold
that up as, "Oh, it's been open sourced," and like I'm sure that's got, it's
done some good for the world. But like I can't use, I can't go build a car,
right? Um, software is just files, digital files on a computer, st- lists of
strings of characters that I can, if I have enough disk space, like actually
hold and then actually manipulate and then actually, like I can try to build
that car because I have everything I need to do it on the device that is the
computer. And so the idea of saying, "I'm gonna make everything free," who cares
if you do that with a car? It's not a thing that people can really attainably
actually leverage as open source. Open source, giving away software is to give
away the entire value of that software that you've created. You, you're not-
Yeah, well you-
... gonna be able to monetize that through the existing-
You're definitely touching on an important-
... I invented it port that people are used to-
Yeah
... if you go open source-
Totally
... your software, right? And part of that is the code. Like because it's just
code written down, we can move it around through the idea system instead of
having to move it through the physical world. [chuckles]
Well, you're touching on another really critical part of software that makes it
a weird n- space. It's entirely virtual. Uh, maybe that's not the right word,
but it's, it's, it's fungible, right? You can reproduce it an infinite number of
times, and it kind of doesn't cost anything, and everyone can have it. Uh,
whereas the car, like in, in service of later parts of this conversation, I
think the open source concept with hardware makes sense too, and we're seeing a
lot of that also. But it's just so much harder. You have to go buy... The cost
of a car is mostly captured in the parts, right? There's, the company's gotta
make profit, but you have to go buy an engine and like physically get it to your
house, and they're really heavy. And it's still complicated and challenging.
There's still all kinds of engineering, uh, necessary to put a car together, uh,
just like getting a computer up and running from scratch. But y- it, there's no
cost. If you have a computer already, to add software to it, there's, there
doesn't need to be a cost. The value of buying software is like entirely
artificial, right? And, and I mean that in like an economic sense, right? A, a,
a, a car, the company who made the car for you has to, at the very least, like
pay for the steel that the car is made out of, right? They can't get around
that. They can't give you a car without having paid for that steel. With
software, they wrote it, and fine, that costs them money, but now they could
just give out the software to everyone, which you can't do that anywhere else.
You can't do that in the physical world. And so that's an incredibly distinct
component, uh, of open source software. And what's-
This is maybe-
... dri- driven it, right, and allowed it
Well, and this is maybe a, a tangent, but like this is also I think is the
fundamental thing that people struggle with in cybersecurity conversations. The
scariest thing about the idea that the 2020 bar exam might get hacked is
everything is digitally replicable one for one at the speed of the internet. So
for this two-day, eight-hour-a-day test, if someone finds an exploit on day one,
every hacker in the world knows about it and how to do it and has the, has the
hardware and the access to execute it for eight hours the next day.
Yeah.
Like, and people are like, "Yeah, well." It's like n- it immediately like seems
to break the human scale brain-
[chuckles] Yeah
... when you, when you, when you take away scarcity. Uh-
Yeah, you certainly can't... This stuff, this snowballs so quickly, right? You
can't talk about open source software, or you shouldn't, without talking about
the internet, right? 'Cause now all of a sudden, to continue the car analogy, if
I am tinkering with my car at home, say I've got a machine shop in my garage and
I like mill myself a turbocharger and install it on my own car, I can tell
people about that, right? I can go tell my friend. I can go help them in their
shop build one, and cool, we've both hacked our car. But I can't put it on the
internet and have every car in the world all of a sudden have a turbocharger,
right? That's what happens with software. It, it, and, and with the internet,
right? I can, I can go into a piece of software and I can make a change, and
anyone who wants that change now can just come have it. And in the modern world,
they can come have it instantaneously, right? There's systems set up to just pr-
to instantly make these upgrades as they're contributed to open source projects,
which realizing we're way ahead of ourselves on-
Yeah
... depth, right? We need to-
No, but I mean that, but it gets to the next-
Bring it back in a little bit and explain
... the next point that I wanted to make was like, okay, so, so we're starting
from the, the, the fact of code exists and software's weird, blah, blah, blah,
right? Uh, the next thing, and this is the part that blows my mind when I talk
to like professionals about it, we have to talk about the extent to which
without open source thinking, literally none of the stuff that we are d- that we
just talked about, all that internet shit, your email, text messages, uh, uh,
uh, uh, uh, uh, this conversation we're having right now via video chat doesn't
exist without open source projects, and I don't think people understand that,
right? Like, I think a lot of people's conception of the internet is like Steve
Jobs invented it in 1984, and they're geniuses, and that's why Apple should have
so much money, and that's not really the evolution of this stuff. Like, if you
wanna get real deep on it, we have episodes about routing protocols and about
how the internet works. But like ultimately, what we're talking about is, you
know, like the movement that is the meme, the notion of open software, that idea
where somebody just went, "Well, let's just give this one away. What if we all
agree to not make money off of this? You know, and what we're gonna do is
because this is only protected by license, we're gonna come up with a license
where no one's allowed to use this who doesn't also agree to allow the next
person to use it for free too."
It's a funny impulse, right? And I think at the very least it proves that, uh,
if you reduce the cost to someone to free, we as humans, uh, are in some
capacity altruistic [chuckles] right? It's kind of a proof there. Uh, some
people still aren't. Some people still would never wanna give away something
they worked hard on, and totally makes sense, right? 'Cause that is the opposite
of like how evolution works, right? If you put energy into something, you need
to get it back, or else your lineage is gonna die off. So, uh, it's weird, and
it kind of exists. My head's deep in politics right now, obviously, as I expect
a lot of people are, but it kind of exists in that same philosophical split of
like, do we, do we keep things and capitalize on them entirely to like maintain
control over things in the case of like Windows-
And to extract all the possible value-
Right
... for ourselves, right?
Or, or, or is there like a greater good that can be achieved with long-term
progress by sharing things out? And honestly, it doesn't... You can argue both,
right? Like they're, it's really interesting when you start to look at open
source software versus like closed source software. It's owned by companies.
Right.
Both are hugely successful, and you see these, this like up and down battle over
the last 50 years as, as businesses take these different angles. So it's, uh,
it's really interesting to kind of see those different philosophies play out,
uh, in the space of our world.
And so, yeah, and so ultimately it's, it's, it, you know, it becomes a public
versus private question. You know, so it's not a new challenge, right? You can
literally go read the Federalist Papers if you wanna start to break down the
idea of what is the public good and how should we leverage it in systems of
banking and et cetera, right? Um, and so it, it seems to me that it's just sort
of like an ebb and flow conversation, and, and in the space of collaboration,
there are times for the open piece and there are time for the closed piece, and
they just sort of flow in and out, right? And I think we're living through a
change in that mindset right now, which is why it comes up in politics a lot.
But ultimately, that change is brought on by the technology we're talking about,
right? So the places I like to take it back to with open source is like, never
mind sort of the popular examples we'll get to in a second that I think, you
know, uh, uh... So when we'll start saying names that people might recognize in
terms of brands and things like that [chuckles]. Um, y- you know, it starts at
the idea of what gave us the internet, which is protocols, right? So email works
because everyone that had servers at the time that the internet was being
invented, and that was still enough people that you could go like, "Yo, all
you'cause it's just like a bunch of universities, academics at universities.
Somebody said, "Hey, if we use this codified instruction set to send messages
back and forth," and by codified I mean it's in a code file so it can't work
another way, not like put in laws, which is codified. So, like, then we can send
email back and forth. And all people have been allowed to monetize ever since
then is like, "Hey, here's a novel interface for email." But the reason email
works, like no one-- That's not true. A lot of people listening to this have
probably heard of SMTP, but the people I wanna talk to have never heard of SMTP,
right? It's just the underlying software that makes email work, and email works
as widely as it does because that shit's free.
Yeah. Another interesting piece with the, with the concept of open source that
you see that I think is really, uh, kind of counterintuitive, um, but also like,
again, a recognition of these competing philosophies both having value. Uh, s-
much, some open source licenses, a lot of open source software is allowed to be
shared freely, but also you're allowed to go, like, use it to build a product
and build a business around, which is, like, the ultimate perfect combination,
right? It's like, "Hey, I've, I've made this thing. It-- For whatever reason, I
got the value out of it that I needed. I don't need any more value. Let me pass
it along." Uh, and then-
Yeah. Hey, monetize it if you want
... not only, yeah, not only can you have it-
If you got a better idea than me, like, monetize it
Yeah, totally. Which it's really easy to get caught up in that philosophy and be
like, "Well, that's obviously the way forward, right? Like, if I enable you,
then you enable other people, and like, look at all the abundance that'll come
from that geometric expansion," which, uh, kind of is that, is that philosophy
on that side, right?
Yeah. And, and, and, and you know, I'm, I'm an Apple shareholder for a reason.
Like, there is an argument for, "Hey, take all that stuff, make it actually
usable," [chuckles]
Make it-
"Put it in a shiny box," which just costs money, "and then sell it to people."
[chuckles]
Um, you know, that, that, that gets to exist. They're not like, uh, they're not,
it's not a binary, which is a term I chose carefully. [both laughing] It's not,
it's not a binary, you know, sort of operations system, right?
You're touching on another really critical piece of this, which is, like,
functionality, and this is part of the big argument a lot of the time. Like,
Apple argues that they should have-- They've always had this, this, uh, I don't
know if it's like rules or terms of service or what, but they very, very
strictly control how their software works and how software that you build that
runs on their machines work, right? Apple, anyone who builds software apps for
the Apple Store versus apps for, like, the Google, uh, Google Store or, or, uh,
Android Store, uh, very different process, right? Very strict in how you build
Apple. And so Apple software and then Apple from a hardware perspective does the
same thing, right? You can't just go buy a bunch of parts to, like, build an
Apple computer in the same way that you can with a PC. So the operating system
needs very specific stuff, and so what you get is, like, a very pristinely
clean, uh, physical hardware system and software that runs on it, right? Like,
it just, it's... I know p- I know it's a flame war between Apple and, and
Windows, but it's just, it's silly to have it. Apple stuff runs better.
It's a, yeah.
You might not like it as much-
It's a bullshit flame war
... and it may be different, but, um-
It's a bullshit flame war 'cause the people having it understand why Apple stuff
is better. They just can't afford it.
Yeah. It's not fair to say-
And it makes them pissy
... better either necessarily-
Right? Like-
... right? 'Cause they're, the benefit is that you can do whatever the hell you
want with those other systems, right? I can build anything and throw it on-
Yeah, right
... to an Android phone, whereas there are all kinds of limitations on Apple
phones which actually are really bad. They hold back innovation. Um, like for-
Yeah, for sure. I don't, I mean better in the just sort of like-
Yeah, totally
... 50 million people can't be wrong way. It's like, look, the Apple is worth
what it's worth because that way of doing it works, man. I don't know what to
tell you. Uh, at the same time, none of the stuff I spend all day doing works
if... Like, I spend all day working with people on running Linux on their
laptops. [chuckles] So like-
[chuckles]
And then, but that also means I frequently have to troubleshoot shit for them
because the software doesn't work perfectly. [scoffs] "I can't screen share."
[chuckles]
"Well, are you running Linux?" "Yeah." [sighs] "Okay. Here's the 10 things I
need you to do right now, which includes dropping code into the core Linux
kernel." Like-
Wait, do you run a Linux machine?
No. [chuckles]
You just use... You're right. Okay.
No, I don't. I don't. I got nothing to prove.
[laughs]
[sighs]
It's a struggle if your primary desktop is, like, total open source everything.
No, totally.
Good luck. [laughs]
But, so I mean, and this is kind of the relevant transition without... I, I got,
if you want me to kill 10 minutes on Riot versus Apple in the context of app
stores, I'm, I'm, I'm raging on that, [laughs] that bullshit bad faith
representation-
No, we, we got it
... from Riot of what the fuck happened. But I don't... Anyway, um-
Wait, what's Riot? Oh, is that the, the gaming port?
I think it's Epic. Yeah. Like, they wanna make more money, so they're pulling
their shit out of Apple's App Store, and they're p- the Fort- the company that
makes Fortnite-
I get it
... is throwing their weight around to try to change App Store dynamics.
Which is how the world works, right?
Um-
You just throw your weight around. [chuckles]
Yeah. They just, they have ret- they have referred to a bunch of things as
retaliatory in press releases-
Mm
... that really, it, that, that tack strikes me as particularly bad faith. They
broke a rule, and then Apple automatically did the thing that the store does
when you break that rule.
Yeah.
Which is exactly the mechanism that has protected us for a really long time from
things like money scams.
This is why we need all human emotion removed from every decision that's made.
And then they say it's a retaliation. Well, yeah, like it's a retaliation the
way-- Like, the city's not retaliating against you when they give you a parking
ticket. You broke the fucking rule. They're cites- giving you a citation for
breaking the rule. They're not retaliating against you with an oppressive...
What? Representation of the fact that you broke a rule? It was on the fucking
sign right there. You don't have a right to not obey that rule because your car
is nice. God, Los Angeles has ruined my brain.
Oh, Los Angeles.
Uh, [chuckles] anyway. So that's Riot. That's Riot and Apple. That said, I think
it's time for Apple to probably rethink its App Store dynamics around some of
these things. Like, payments are getting weird again, and we gotta look at that.
Um, but like, you know, Apple literally employs people to make sure that your
things aren't a scam that's, you know, your apps in the store aren't gonna
steal, uh, $10,000 from you and then run away with it, which happens-
Good
... constantly with apps on Android.
And, uh, that touches another interesting place with software, right? If you,
uh, if the software's not protected and taken care of, you can easily get
screwed by it, right? It can take over your computer. It can delete your hard
drive. It can turn your computer into, uh, part of a botnet, which then is going
out and breaking all kinds of laws around the world, doing illegal things, and
you don't even know it's happening.
Yeah, which, like kinda kicks back to the security thing, which is like, you
know, bad code can be really powerful, and that bad code can be open. [chuckles]
[laughs]
So all that is open is not virtuous necessarily, right? Um, and I, I... You
know, like everything we've said to this point, I think sort of gets this thing.
It's like, okay, so you can tell just by the way that we talk, and I hope that
we have otherwise introduced it sufficiently. Like, the idea that there's,
there's a cultural split ultimately between the idea of like this stuff sh- is
the stuff that should be open, this stuff's the stuff that's not. Everyone is in
an ecosystem where we have to acknowledge that open stuff is helpful, 'cause
otherwise we don't have email, you don't have text message. Like, communication
protocols, we're generally pretty good at being like, "Okay, you can't lock that
one down."
I don't, we don't think there's-
We need that to work.
I don't think there's anything... I mean, there, there's no piece of software
that the average person is familiar with that's not, uh, absolutely crippled if
all the open source stuff was pulled out, right? I don't think your car-
No, 100%
... would run, the internet doesn't work, your computer at home wouldn't work.
Every, everything would break instantly.
Google Heartbleed bug.
Every-
Yeah
... the entire world would stop working if we pulled out open source.
The encryption protocols that run the internet work because they're maintained
by a nonprofit who's not allowed to make money-
Mm-hmm
... off of that thing.
Yep.
Like, literally go Google heartbeat, Heartbleed bug.
Yeah, this is not a-
And learn about the 36 hours banks spent thinking they were just c- completely
fucked. [laughs]
There's no, there's no hyperbole in those comments. I, I-
No
... I mean, I'm guessing a little bit that everything, but, um, it, it's... I'm
trying to speak to the how much complexity there is in the layering of software
in the world, right? To make your computer work, to let you video chat, to let
you send a text message, there are just hundreds and hundreds of layers of, of
things interrupting, interrupt- interruptable? [chuckles]
Interacting.
Interacting with each other.
Yeah.
Pieces of software working with each other and relying on each other and doing
these little micro things. And I think a lot of people probably picture an
application as like, uh, just abstract, right? Most people aren't thinking about
software, uh, too frequently and how it works and haven't really worked in it
much. So you maybe think of an application as like a book, right? Here's a
complete thing that I put together. But really it breaks down more as you break
it down into the, into the chapters and the pages and the index and the
sentences and the grammar. All of those could be different software projects
that layer in to make, make the program work. So each chapter in your book or
each sentence in your book could be a different piece of software, and a bunch
of those are almost always open source. They're things that you can just go look
'em up. Anyone can use them. They're freely available. Um, because part of
what's neat, again, with software where you, where you really quickly hit all
these interesting philosophical places is there kind of are, you are able to do
things, at least at a very small scale when you're looking at a very tiny,
specific, well-defined problem in computer science. You kind of can do them in
the best way, and everyone can say, "Okay, that's the optimal program. Let's use
that one now." Um, it usually breaks down at a lower level than just the
software. Um-
Yeah
... but-
I would say it allows for a system where the optimal solution emerges.
That's certainly true, too. That's what-
Which is a really crazy way to say it, right?
... the open source helps be.
I mean, you can-
Yeah
... you can have agreement that this is the right way to solve it, or you can
have this way that everybody seems to use and it hasn't broken, and okay, we're
all good with it.
Well, that's usually actually where it ends up, which is funny to notice, is
that it ends up, you recognize that there is the, there is the ability to
optimize and come up with the best way to do something. But what you realize is
that in the organic world, what really ends up winning is popularity again, even
in software. This thing was just adopted. And I don't mean popularity in the
sense that like, "Ooh, everyone loves this one the most. He's the coolest. Let's
elect him, uh, prom king and queen." But it just is the one that got used the
most, uh, incidentally, and now-
Yeah
... you have to keep using it because everything runs on it.
And so there's, there's... You know, what's interesting with that, that gets us
into the sort of emergence of... Like, the last thing we gotta talk about is Git
and version control, and then after we've explained that, I think we can really
jump off the cliff of like-
[laughs]
... why this creates weird tribes of open source developers who all believe
different memes and, eh, believe in different cryptocurrencies. But, like,
fundamentally, it's this layered system, and all of those systems are complex,
and all of those systems talk to one another, and it's all code, so it's all
really rigid. If you're off by a comma, the shit just doesn't work.Right.
Mm-hmm.
So that's the nature of all of the interconnected things, right? And some are
open, some are closed, and then you have this emergent situation that we've,
that we sort of, I think have introduced. On the open side-- On the closed side,
there's a limited team maintaining that software, right? Apple's gonna push
updates to fix things. Everybody's used to this cycle now in the modern world,
right?
Mm-hmm.
Like, you get software updates, they're for security, they're for usability,
they're for prettier buttons, whatever the, you know, whatever, right? They have
a limited team there, I don't know, 1,000 people in Cupertino, that is their dev
squad working on X, Y, and Z thing, right? Uh, an open source project with
500,000 contributors has 500,000 programmers always watching that code base and
going, "Ooh, I don't like that bug. I'm gonna squash it. Oh, that's dangerous.
We should all try to fix that right now full-time until it's fixed."
Mm-hmm.
And then eight hours later, the bug is squashed and out of the software
[chuckles] like-
Yeah, that's, that's the concept for sure.
Um-
I mean, it, it probably, if you look at numbers, it kind of scales similarly.
Yeah, no, I mean, right. It's wicked-
Which again, is an interesting place where it-
Right
... where like these phil- philosophies, uh, parallel each other, right? Um,
God, software's such an interesting point to look at philosophy. [chuckles]
Right. Okay, so let's back up though, 'cause all I, I, you know, introducing all
that stuff, the last thing to understand is then Git was invented.
Yeah.
Uh, version con- So, so you can imagine how this would be a clusterfuck of human
coordination, like trying to take on, like... And this is why it ebbs and flows.
It was hard to develop software 'cause you have to keep this code base in sync.
Like, and so as your team gets bigger, that becomes harder to do because of all
of that layers of-
Right
... all of those layers of complexity. And eventually you get to a point where
it's just like, eh, it's not worth having a dev team of X size 'cause we do more
harm than good when we go off and work on different, like, components of this
layered up system. Uh...
Yeah. Imagine if, if every ti- Imagine, uh, I'm gonna try to give an example of
this. Even, and this is not-
Goddammit, Dave missed a comma again. I spent all day-
[chuckles] Version-
... trying to figure out why this wouldn't even load. Like, uh, you know?
[chuckles]
Version control is not a, is not distinct, distinctly needed just for open
source. It's needed for any sort of software where there's collaboration, 'cause
imagine if when you wrote a book, if like at the end, when you're done writing,
like done writing for the day, if you missed that comma somewhere in the book,
the book is unreadable, right? The whole book can't be read.
Yeah. [chuckles]
It can't sit on your shelf. The shelf catches on fire. Um-
You can't even look at it to find out which-
But you can't even-
... which comma you fucked up
... you can't even find it. The book disappears from reality until someone like
goes into the reality and fixes the comma.
[chuckles]
Now imagine you've got 100 people writing the book together, right? And some
people are working on the same sentence at the same time. And so I might edit
the sentence different than you did, and whether or not the sentence-- Let's say
we both made the sentence work right, so the book renders in the world later and
people can read it. It still di- we both changed the sentence differently, so
how do we like put the book back together? And so that is a really challenging
prob- pro- problem, and I think people run into this a lot now actually, 'cause
most software is collaborative and most software is run online in, in the cloud,
in quote, thrown quotes up. But, um, so you h- you see that on like Google
Spreadsheets. If you're both-
Yeah
... in there, you can see where the other person is, you can see what they're
doing, which like sort of prevents you from editing stuff at the same time, but-
Right
... that's even different 'cause with software, I'm editing a different piece
of-- Like I'm cloning the car, messing with the engine, and then we're trying to
like push those two clones of the car back into one car again. So there's this
wild complexity in how that's managed, and, uh, Git, like you mentioned, is, is
like the predominant, uh, version control now, and GitHub, which a lot of people
have probably heard-
Which is really just like Git, Git is a software codified methodology for
maintaining these files.
Mm-hmm.
That's it, right? And so you go boop-boop-boop, and you got Git running on your
document.
Yep. And even, and even with Git, which is again like the most developed, and
coincidentally, I think Git was developed by Linus Torvalds, who also invented
Linux, so he's like really spiraling into the-
He needed-
... the realm of fantasy superhero
... it's the necessary tool to-
Right
... create the big open, the most successful open source project.
So even, even with that, like the best thing the world has been able to invent
for collaborative software development, it's still kind of a nightmare a lot of
the time to like keep your software working. It's just frustrating and like
you're like, "Oh man, we gotta, you gotta sit down with the other person and
work through all this stuff, or the whole team, and like edit things and fight
over like, 'Well, should we do it this way? Should we do it that way?'" So
there, it's not like you push a button and all of your software works again. I
know that's-
Right
... kind of the concept everyone wants it to be.
Yeah. But it's, but you n- Part of it is [chuckles]...
It is sometimes.
There's a, there's part of being a software developer that I think is hard to
appreciate if you're coming from other sectors. There's a time in almost every
one of my days where I go, "Okay, I'm gonna press this button, and after I do,
my company's website might crash."
[chuckles] Right.
And then my boss is gonna call me and go, "What the fuck happened to the
website? We're not selling things anymore."
Right.
Right? And so we have put in place rollback things where you can-- I've
literally had days where that heart-sinking feeling where you're just, you
realize you just pushed something bad up to the live thing, and then you go
like, I have crashed WordPresses, live WordPress builds for e-commerce stores
with significant amounts of traffic.
[chuckles] Right.
And I knew how to have that only be down for an hour with backup protocols, but
like it's a real thing you deal with if you're a developer in this space, just
in a professional context. Like Apple has, Apple uses this shit too.
Yeah.
[chuckles] So-
Yeah, I mean, so we, we hit on another interesting piece of software, or an
interesting aspect of software, and this is not always true, right? 'Cause
software runs everything, right? Your car runs on software, planes run on
software, spaceships, the electrical grid, everything. But like in the, in the
day-to-day w- that I think most people think of software now, like apps on your
phone, they're just not very importantIf your app on your, if some silly app on
your phone that lets you play Candy Crush or like send a text message doesn't
work for the day, really doesn't matter. Um, and so you're able to iterate kind
of in the sense of like there's so many bacteria out in the world that it
doesn't matter as they like die really quickly and iterate and, and evolve and
genetic difference happens. That was a weird analogy to pull out.
It's, it's high volume.
[laughs] But anyway.
Like that's what all we have left is biology when we start to talk about
internet numbers.
Yeah.
There are trillions of apps.
You can't, you can't do that with a car. If I, if you open sourced my, my brake
system, and then all of a sudden anyone could be editing it and you could push
the brake updates to everyone else's cars [laughs] if they were there-
And then your brakes don't work also? Yeah.
Right. All the cars blow up. So-
Right. [laughs]
... um, there is an interesting, there's ... And again, software runs all kinds
of important stuff that's outside of the, the world of like willy-nilly, silly
Silicon Valley crap.
Yeah.
[laughs] Like dating apps and text messaging apps and slight iterations on
email. But the, uh, that's an important component of it, right? Is you n- to be
able to iterate quickly on this stuff, you have to set up a, a means by which
there cannot, there can be critical failure, uh, is kind of removed from the
situation.
And so, and so here's my like sort of media theorist take on the fundamental
thing that Git achieved, uh, and that we need to roll out in some capacity to
every other version of life, uh, where we, you know, in work and whatever. Um,
and you s- like you already said, you already cited the places where it's
happening, right? Like versions of this way of thinking of a thing are just,
it's infectious. And so, and, and it, it also gets us to things like blockchain,
uh, which is the way Git, Git tracks literally every single change that happens
in the underlying code that is your document. You can use it on a Word doc, you
can use it on simpler files, you can use it on wildly complex files, and it just
keeps a record of every change that was ever made. And crucially, at least
theoretically, a canonical record.
Mm-hmm.
So the change and what time, literally of day, but also in what sequence with
the other changes every change was made. And when you think of that, it feels
like, uh, this kind of gets back to our, our, our like Wolfram episode. Git
stopped saying, "Okay, I have a document. You made some changes. Save. Now
that's a new document." [laughs]
Mm-hmm.
Git said, "I'm just gonna save the extra data. I'm only gonna save what changed
and a record of how and when that change was made." And then the file only grows
by a tiny bit relative to the size of the other file. [laughs] And so you can
have this piggyback on your thing that's just always going, "And then this
change happened, and then this person did this thing, and then this person did
this thing."
Right.
And at any time you can go back and go, "Okay, that changed, and then it
crashed. Okay, I'm gonna take out just that change, and everything else should
still work. It works. Okay, put it back up." [laughs] Like-
And I mean, again-
Uh
... that's another place where you start to touch on kind of underlying
philosophies of the world, right? The, the universe, as best as we can tell, is
keeping track of all the changes, right? When a change is made, it's, it's,
it's-
There. [laughs]
... a law of, of thermodynamics, right? It, it-
Yeah
... if, if you make a change here, it changes something else, and so that, the
change that you made here is captured in the change in the other thing. And so
that's kind of what you do here because anyone who, especially if you work in
like the modern data world as we're seeing the explosion in how important
information is, uh, you just, you, y- your urge is to capture everything because
even if you don't know how it's useful now, you know it's gonna be useful in a
year or a month or a day because the ability to have that information and do
things with it is just expanding. And so it's, it's interesting that it's
evolved to capture those changes, right? It, it would seem trivial with writing
a novel, right? To capture every single time you subtly edited like the, the,
uh, language of, of each sentence, right? "Oh, I moved, I, I changed this word
to give a subtly different meaning or to describe something in a way that's,
that's slightly different." Certainly useful some for the writer as the book's
coming together, but ultimately you don't need every single change to be
tracked. It's just not relevant. But with software it really can be, right? You
have to go back and see how things happen, and you wanna be able to roll back,
and you wanna be able to see why, why were these explicit decisions made, which
maybe begs the question, is that important for books? Should books be open
source and forever changing? Like that's an interesting concept.
Well-
[laughs]
... I think the last piece to hit-
Spitball
... is one more core thing that's only doable because of software, which is this
is kept in a, in a, in what's called an append only sort of, I'm just gonna call
it methodology, right? 'Cause the thing is you can make the code work. The idea
is the rule of your database is you can't delete an old entry. You can just
invalidate it by reference. And so when you have an append-only methodology for
record keeping, you-- Like it's, it's, uh, it's, it's more like keeping a, like
your checkbook or something, right? Um, if you send out a check, you have to
account for that ch- like I don't, I don't wanna t-teach people how to balance
their checkbooks.
[laughs]
But the point is like you can't just go back and delete an old entry. Instead
you have to put up a new change that says, "Now ignore this." Uh, oh, I, I screw
up constantly, and I have to roll back and make a change, and the funny thing is
I'm just constantly aware that my record of like, "And then he put this up and
fucked this up and fucked that up, and then there was another one," like is
still there, which is kind of funny.
Right. Yep.
But it's there because I know that the underlying infrastructure isn't possible
of letting me go back and erase it'Cause that's how the record is kept so that
we can achieve the thing that we achieve. And the idea of saying, like, if you
try to imagine how to do that, like, with typewriters in a law office, it's
like, okay, that-- I mean, you could maybe almost do it there because of how
typewriters work. But if you imagine doing that with word processors in an
office, it's kinda like, okay, I deleted this line. I, I fixed it. Now the
document's updated. Like, why is that a system that doesn't work, right? So, so
when you apply it to old models, it, it's weird to think of this idea of like,
well, we don't have the... Again, it's a scarcity thing, right? We try to clear
out space to put the new stuff in just as, as humans [chuckles] in our brains.
But software allows it to just say, no, the rule inside of Git is if you're
gonna run Git, the rule is here's how this append-only structure works, right?
And so it really does make every single little change trackable. You really can
do the thing that you're talking about because of that fundamental thing at the
core of how this, like, methodology works, right? [lip smack] Um, when you stack
all of that up, y- you, you can work on these massively complex projects
together w- with the right coordination, which a lot of times people will at
this point have heard of GitHub, if only because Microsoft bought them for a
shit ton of money. Uh, GitHub is essentially just a social platform on top of
Git. So a way of talking about all the work that you did that was tracked by
these things and st- and maintained interoperability because of the work that
you did, and created a social layer, essentially, of people that are like, "Yo,
let's all work on this project together."
Mm-hmm.
With Linux, that was, you know, Git was developed because they were tired of
doing that via email, and then GitHub popped up because people were tired of
however they were coordinating this thing whilst not breaking the software
amongst a bunch of people that just cared to work on the project. Like, just
open source gets social really quickly, and so there's this weird social aspect
of what we end up talking about with communities and, and, uh, like that piece
of it. Um, but I think that's everything sort of technical, right? I mean,
fundamentally, the place we're at now is we can make software, we can
collaborate on it without breaking the software. A- a- a- and, and, and you
start looking at other places to apply it. Like, it just, you just get to weird
things I find myself explaining to lawyers all the time, which is like, "This
thing, this thing we just templated, no one should ever have to do that again."
[laughs] Yeah, that is-
There's no fucking reason.
That is a funny concept, 'cause you're right.
And they go, "What? No."
We've re- we've reached a point where, uh, for the most part, almost ev- it
feels like almost everything has an open source counterpart, right? Like, think
of a popular piece of software, uh, and there's an open source version, right?
Like Photoshop, yep, open source version. Microsoft Office, all of them have
open source versions. Not only do you have, like, the free versions that, like,
Google makes available to you, but you can just go get multiple different
versions that have large communities that, like, rebuilt Microsoft Word. Uh,
it's a little different. It does things differently, sometimes doesn't interop.
[chuckles] There, I'm trying to use interoperability again. Sometimes it doesn't
work with the other, other tools. Um, it works fine within its own environment.
And so as a developer, like, as you're building things... This is funny. I'm
making a really interesting connection to my previous engineering work before
software. But as you're building software, you, you, you're using other software
to build your software, right? You're building on top of it. And so whenever you
need a piece of software to do anything, you go search for it first. Like, did
someone build this already? Did someone solve this problem? It, the concepts
that you, like, learn academically, and I'm not a computer scientist, so I'll
often misspeak about this stuff. But I think the concepts, um, [lip smack] are,
uh, are called design patterns, and that's kinda what you learn academically,
these, like, reduced concepts that you see over and over and over again in
engineering and in software. And so, like, you'll see this, you'll see this
thing which is like, they'll, they'll be very low level, like how do you solve
this logic problem? You'll see them over and over and over again in your
software, and they'll manifest in different ways. But when, when you see this,
be aware of it and know that the complexity of it has been reduced and solved in
this way, and you should always kinda do it this way unless you have a really
good reason not to. Um, kinda like how grammar works in, in written, written and
spoken language. And so you learn that, but we've reached like a meta level
where so much of the next layer of complexity, like how does this software work
in this language, on this operating system, with this hardware, in this use
case? You just go get it. Someone's built it, and 100 people have helped
maintain it. And so we're, we're in a interesting place where so much stuff can
be pieced together, and software's too complicated still to, for that to just be
like plug and play. Anyone can just, like, touch things together and have them
work. But [lip smack] and, uh, you know, it, it touches on th- that realization
that I called out there a second ago that was so interesting compared to my old
job where I worked in physical manufacturing. I was a manufacturing engineer. I
constantly was frustrated by having to reinvent things that I knew had been
solved hundreds or thousands of times all around the world, right? In a
manufacturing plant where I was building automation, I was building robotics and
automating manufacturing processes, I constantly had to solve something. I was
like, "This is so simple and silly, but it's not, like, a thing I can go buy."
It's, like, ever so complex that whoever has solved this a thousand times before
in a thousand different manufacturing plants, they didn't have, like, a means to
share it.
You should be the one doing it.
I shouldn't have to do this again. And that-
Yeah, you just pitched your first startup.
Exactly. That's what drove, that's what drove me to my first startup. And, and I
didn't realize what it was at the time. I wasn't actually trying to solve that
problem. Um, I was solving something different, related, but... And soThe
concept of open source being released into the world more broadly than software
is really challenging because it seems to, it works best and maybe arguably only
works when things are digitized, which is not true of, like, physical things
like car parts, um, although the designs are all digitized now. But it just, it
enables such an incredible layering of, like, success and invention and
creativity, and it also makes it so apparent how important other people's
contributions to things are, right? It makes it s- there's, there's nothing that
any modern s- programmer does for the most part that would be even, even, like,
imaginable without the incredible underpinnings of everything that, that allow
it to happen. Like, modern technology, especially in software and hardware and
computers, is so complicated that no one really knows how it all works anymore.
And, and I don't mean at, like, a high level I can tell you how a computer
works, but I could not even come freaking close to being functional with, like,
99.99% of what's out there. Even in a lifetime-
That's fine
... it's just too complicated now, right?
Well, you don't-
And it doesn't-
It doesn't matter
Well, that's exactly the thing.
You don't speak certain languages.
I don't need to.
So you can get an interpreter. [laughs]
We talk about this sometimes. I wonder, I wonder how this felt h- even, uh, even
just a few hundred years ago when you have, like, the concept of, of, like, a
jack of all trades or what's the fancier word for that type of person?
Generalist?
Generalist, yeah, where you like-
[laughs]
I feel like you-
That's what I call myself
... you almost kind of could know everything in a lifetime a few hundred years
ago. If you were s- extraordinarily well-read, you could be up to date on, like,
everything that's really known in modern science and modern medicine and
chemistry. There just wasn't as much happening. And I, I know there's subtlety
in, like, the human experience that can't be known and, and emotion and, and how
you perceive the world, but in terms of kinda like raw scientific knowledge, you
could know such a larger percentage of it, uh-
Right
... in times of past, right? And now it's absolutely impossible, right? Even
pick the, pick the most specific niche and you can't know it all anymore. Um, so
we've reached a point where we have to open source stuff. We have to open source
information, and we have to exist in a world where you can trust what's been
open sourced, because if you can't, then you can't make progress anymore. We
can't go-
Even-
... forward if you can't trust the layer that's beneath you.
Even if you hear that and, and, like, have a violent reaction to it, it doesn't
matter. It's happening, right? Like, this is also just a force that is not even
guided. It's, it's, technology is a force unto itself that's doing what it
wants-
Yeah
... with us whether we like it or not.
I mean, I-
[laughs] Like-
It's a weirder-
Wikipedia exists, right? You, like-
Yeah
... you might say, "No, we need to keep that locked in an encyclopedia." Sorry,
the Wikipedia box is unlocked and it runs. Like, it slaps. [laughs]
Yeah. And, and-
And so-
... and people are doing everything. There's so many projects to maintain that,
right? There are people printing it out regularly and stashing it in vaults so
we never lose it. There are people putting it on, on media that will last for m-
millions of years and hiding it and preserving it and constantly updating it as
it's updated. Like, this, this stuff has meaning and, and we-
Writing it on gold records and firing it billions of miles from the Earth.
[laughs]
We should definitely launch Wikipedia out on some satellites.
For sure.
[laughs]
Uh, but yeah, like, so there's, there's two things to wrap up. If you're also
one of those people that listens and hears about cryptocurrencies and DeFi and
blockchain and that part of what we talk about, the application of this way of
thinking about the world to finance is why that has captured some subset of
every young person's mind that I have talked to. They understand what you can do
with this-
Mm-hmm
... and they're taking down the banks. They're just tired of it.
Yeah.
[laughs] They're tired of being oppressed by our financial system. And so, hey,
like, w- uh, what will happen? I don't know. But this tiny subset has the tool
we just described, and they're using it for money. To not watch that is just
ignorant. Like [laughs] I don't know how, I don't know how else to say it.
Let me spin it the other way, too. Uh, it, we're just, we just see the
opportunity and we're tired of not executing on it, right? The, the-
Right
... the systems that came before when they were new were fucking fantastic, and
those people were just as thrilled as we are to innovate. But there's so many
places we can innovate, and innovation happens so much easier now when it's
allowed to that it's even more frustrating when you see the opportunity and it's
not being executed on. So comparatively now to 50 or 100 or a couple hundred
years ago when a lot of things that exist now that people are so fed up with
were being established, we can fix them at a faster rate. We can iterate and
improve at a faster rate. We can do it more successfully. We can do it more
collaboratively. We can do it more science and technology and statistically
based. And so it's just, like, ever increasingly obvious to us that we're
wasting time, we're wasting energy when you have to exist inside these systems
that aren't operating at efficiencies that we know are just around the corner.
We're pissed off. And especially when that expands out into beyond, like, simple
things like I, I don't wanna pay a fee when I overdraw my checking account.
Fine, I get that you extract money there. That helps run the business, but
that's fucking stupid. Don't do that anymore.
Also once every three years-
It doesn't need to happen
... the fucking bank loses a lawsuit about fraudulently charging those, and they
have to return a bunch of money to us.
Right. So let's, let's just-
Why the fuck do you even trust that system?
Right. Let's just fix it. Let's fix it.
Anyway, so-
We're off, we're, we're out of control.
Yeah, right. Anyways, so that's financial, right? But the l- the other piece,
and, and this is backing up to the idea of the generalist, right? Which is, you
know, I, I think-Like you were saying, jack of all trades, right? You could know
how to do a bunch of things around a town at some point. My life as a producer,
then as a project manager, and everything I've ever done has been like, like
people say, "What does a producer do on a movie?" Uh, a producer knows who to
talk to and in what order, and that's it. And then they help you with creative
things, right? Um, and there are people that are better at the creative piece,
and they make f- more fun things. But like fundamentally, you can maintain a job
as a producer around Hollywood if you know who to talk to and in what order.
[chuckles]
Right? And, and, uh, if that's not, like... If that's not a perfect articulation
for where this starts to consume knowledge work, is like just knowing that I
should talk to a lawyer is the first step, right? When, if you're talking about
consuming the law. Um, so already that's gated by the same mechanism that's
like, "Well, who do you know?" Well, now I can Google.
Yeah. I mean-
So that's already started to fuck with your universe, right?
That same, that same workflow applies to absolutely everything, right? As soon
as it's, it's a project, it's what do I need to know and in what order? And it's
whether-
Right
... whether you go talk to someone or you, or now. It used to be you had to go
talk to somebody, right? Even, even relatively recently. Like as a kid, I would
have to call the library to-- I would ask my mom about something that you would,
I trivially look up a thousand times a day now. And we would call the library,
and someone would go look it up in a book. Which is-
And if you couldn't find it in that one, you had to go to the other one downtown
'cause it was for-
'Cause you called a bigger library
... 'cause it was for a paper, yeah. [laughs]
Which is utter insanity in today's world. [laughs]
But so anyway, the thing is like, uh, it, it, the place where it hits
cryptocurrency and all the weird stuff that's happening right now, and the
reason, like it's, it's all because of all the stuff we just ran through. Which
I hope the, at least the way that we presented it-
[laughs]
... is like, okay, this is what's happening, and it's, it's consuming parts of
the world.
It was an adventure.
Like, uh-
For sure
... uh, it's coming for knowledge work, like sometime soon. And it's not because
AI is gonna think like a lawyer. It's because people with legal training like me
can identify everything a lawyer does that no one should ever have to do again.
Yeah.
Because software exists.
Right.
So, uh-
Which has other, all kinds of other implications. If you're listening-
Right
... and thinking that's scary and awful, totally agree. [laughs]
[laughs]
Right? There's all kinds of scary things to figure out there too, right? But,
uh-
It's still gonna take people to tend it, so it's like c- that, that's, that's
where we've ended up with Juris. Go learn how to tend it. That's, that's your
legal engineering certification, right? Totally different subset. People will
have jobs. We're probably fine. There'll probably be two for every lawyer that
used to exist. Um-
You know, it's easy to be excited about this stuff when you're involved in
making it. [laughs]
That's true. Uh-
And probably horrifying if you're not.
So that's-
Right?
No, it's-
So-
I mean, it's also, it's also horrifying to be in it 'cause does it work or not,
right?
It's also horrifying.
And does it work or not boils down to this funny thing with open source, which
is you have to-- it, everything is a test of this is one that should be open and
this is one that shouldn't. And, you know, different things win different pieces
of the pie there, right? Like-
Yeah
... cryptocurrency is a place where the government might be like, "Too many
people get hurt if we don't do this through the existing infrastructure. I'm
sorry, y'all."
Mm-hmm.
And they'll shut it down.
That happens all the time.
Uh, to some degree.
And sometimes that's right.
Yeah.
And often it's, it's not. [chuckles] Often it's the wrong decision.
Um-
Oh, I used, I used a word that's not a real word.
Wrong.
Yep. There's one thing I've learned from doing this podcast. It's anytime I use
a word like wrong or better, uh, any sort of judgmental word, I'm, I'm making
something up. [laughs] It's not a real thing, and-
Yeah. The thing-
... it, it has no real bearing on the world. It's just me.
Been reading the-
Just my own bullshit
... Federalist Papers.
[laughs]
And it's interesting, like y- they, they're, you know, more tactful statesmen
and better writers than I will ever be. Uh, they still occasionally go to that
place, right? Like-
It's hard not to
... you're having this, I think, very politically correct thing of like, let's
try to pull out from an impassioned perspective. Eh, Hamilton does an awful lot
of, "I understand this is an impassioned perspective-
[laughs]
... but if we cannot keep in our minds the notion of a public good, we're fucked
'cause Spain is gonna come attack us and take us over." And he means it
literally. [laughs]
Yeah.
Like-
And it's so, you know, there's a time to express that a thing is wrong. I don't
know what to, I don't know what to say otherwise, right? Um, I don't think we do
too-- I, uh, uh, that's not true. We do a shitload of this on this podcast, but
whatever.
Oh, yeah. There's a lot of personality that comes out.
Sorry about that shit. [laughs]
Quite a bit.
Anyway, thanks for hanging out for episode 98.
98. Whew.
On open source and something and-
It was a good adventure
... why robots will replace you. I don't, I, I, you know.
No.
I don't know.
We're a long ways from robots replacing anything. We're not even gonna bother.
Why robots will replace your children?
That one's so obvious we're not even gonna bother with robots anymore. We're
just gonna have glasses on soon, and then we'll be in that episode of "Star
Trek" where Riker brings that weird game back from that, like-
Oh, yeah
... fantasy party planet.
That's fucking TikTok, man.
Yep. Totally.
Where he ate the little swallows, the little discs-
Yep, the little disc swallow
... in like bad povray-
Yep
... 3D animation.
Yep. Who saves the day? Does Wesley save the day on that one? I think so.
I don't, I don't remember.
Even Data I think got sucked into it.
Yeah.
Which was like kind of a cop-out, but maybe not.
I thought Data was just busy with something else. [laughs]
[laughs] Maybe he was away. He was on an away mission. [laughs]
[laughs] Fixed. Rhetorical device.
Oh, boy.
Anyway, I'm Adam.
I'm Brian. Keep an open mind, everybody, and share, and share stuff. Actually,
let me rewind. Just share some things. Go share something with somebody.
[upbeat music] They don't know what I know. They don't know like I know. All the
time. They can't arrive. All the time